<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">To hope or to weep? Slow hope in Rohan Chakravarty&apos;s green humour series</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Arundhathi</forename><surname>Baburaj</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Girish</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Pawar</surname></persName>
							<email>girishpawarhcu@uohyd.ac.in</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of English</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Hyderabad</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hyderabad</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of English</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Humanities</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Hyderabad</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>500046</postCode>
									<settlement>Hyderabad</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Arundhathi Baburaj http://orcid</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>0009-0002-3933-6444</postCode>
									<settlement>Girish D. Pawar</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">To hope or to weep? Slow hope in Rohan Chakravarty&apos;s green humour series</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9E0253ECA8C01B6C065EE0FE2187AFC5</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1080/17449855.2026.2617472</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2026-02-25T19:51+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Slow hope</term>
					<term>decolonial ecology</term>
					<term>subaltern environmentalism</term>
					<term>green humour</term>
					<term>decolonial hope Comics, coloniality, and slow hope</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Rohan Chakravarty's green humour comic series provides hopeful narratives of environmental conservation and justice by focusing on the tenets of decoloniality and subaltern environmental activism catalysed through the use of humour. This article argues that "green humour" ridicules colonial and neo-liberal capitalist interventions in the environment and functions as a counter-hegemonic force by challenging environmental injustices and extractive practices, while presenting Indigenous environmental activism as an alternative. Drawing on Christof Mauch's concept of "slow hope", which focuses on community-based conservation stories and modes of resistance with gradual, often invisible impacts, the article argues that through the use of green humour and vulnerable narrators, Chakravarty reimagines hope beyond western, hierarchical frameworks. By focusing on Indigenous conservation stories and activism, his green humour series espouses a sustainable and decolonial planetary vision that inspires decolonial hope. The article also explores green humour's political potential in confronting ecological crises and consolidating marginalized voices.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Rohan Chakravarty is an Indian cartoonist and comic artist whose works on the environment, vulnerable ecosystems, extinct and endangered animals, and ecopolitics have attracted worldwide acclaim. His green humour series comprises three books of eco-comics: Green Humour for a Greying Planet <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chakravarty 2021)</ref>, Pugmarks and Carbon Footprints <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2023)</ref>, and Sea Ice? Now You Don't <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2024)</ref>. Green humour can be broadly defined as humour that seeks to evoke laughter by making fun of those human interventions to the environment that result in the planetary crisis. Faye D'Souza, in the "Advance Praise for the Book", describes green humour as "a brand of humour that is funny and tragic" (quoted in <ref type="bibr">Chakravarty 2021, n.p.)</ref>. The term "green humour" which he coins has as its primary aim, in Akanksha Sood <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Singh's (2023)</ref> words, to "put the lens of humour on our way of looking at the natural world". Singh adds that the series has a threefold purpose: to enlighten by breaking down scientific jargon, to make the content easily comprehensible for everyone, and to engage the readers emotionally (vii).</p><p>Historically, humour has been accorded a lower status in the hierarchy of affects. Aristotle's lost chapter on comedy maintained that it was an imitation of inferior people. Yet today, literary and visual media such as comics, graphic novels, and TV series and talkback shows all use humour as a counter-hegemonic force capable of critiquing injustice and exposing systemic failures. They demonstrate that, as a mode of epistemological resistance, it subverts dominant modes of thinking and dismantles powerful ideologies and affects. According to Maxwell <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Boykoff and Beth Osnes (2018)</ref>, humour can create new ways of thinking and acting about anthropogenic climate change (1). Satire, irony, camp, irreverence, and unseriousness have a major role in establishing an alternative mode of environmental discourse, and rejecting the totalizing affects of western environmentalism, which privileges emotions such as gloom, seriousness, reverence, and austerity <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Seymour 2018)</ref>. Michael <ref type="bibr">Branch (2014, 13)</ref> advises the use of humour as a "sword" (a weapon of critique) and a "shield" (a means of resilience and healing). By facilitating shared laughter, humour builds community and collective identity and it can foreground subaltern modes of resistance. Nicole <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Seymour (2018)</ref> considers humour to be a crucial tool in exposing the underlying intersections between environmentalism and whiteness, masculinity, and elitism (5). It also encourages a certain degree of selfreflexivity, a fundamental tool in questioning the fairness and inclusivity of the environmental movement (26).</p><p>In the green humour series, for instance, techniques like satire, sarcasm, irony, wordplay, and ridicule are used to criticize western-centric extractive thinking and to amplify marginalized modes of conservation. Green humour requires pause and reflection, rather than instant consumption. The comics exaggerate the role of systemic injustices -emanating from colonialism and capitalism -in environmental decline, in order to reclaim agency for subaltern groups and non-human beings, and to recentre the environmentalist movement on the local and Indigenous. In taking an activist approach to systemic change, green humour provides a crucial channel for the marginalized to urge the powerful to be accountable for environmental decline, thereby offering slow, decolonial hope. Chakravarty's collection features decolonial narratives of hope, in their display of marginalized populations triumphing over environmental challenges posed by First World countries, and stories of community and collective action from Indigenous groups with their modes of activism, resistance, and appeals. The hope featured in these comics is slow, as it rejects quick fixes and prioritizes sustained and counter-hegemonic efforts. It also advocates collective action -rather than individual responses -and community-building, defining features of subaltern environmentalism. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> in Chakravarty's blog shows how Indigenous knowledge systems are excluded from major policy decisions and conservation forums (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). The "peripheral" knowledge and exclusionary conservation practices of the western world are contrasted with local knowledge systems generated by those who are affected the most by environmental decline.</p><p>The reason for selecting the comic genre to discuss in these ecological contexts, and specifically Chakravarty's green humour series, lies in its marginality and ability to deviate from genre conventions and canons. Eco-comics can be broadly defined as a subcategory of the comic genre that focuses on nature, its destruction, the impact of this destruction on human and non-human species, and, at times, how it can be reversed or resolved. In Eco-Comix: Essays on the Environment in Comics and Graphic Novels, Sidney I Dobrin (2020, 1) assigns a threefold function to eco-comics: first, as texts to be read ecocritically; second, as texts that circulate environmental rhetoric; and third, as texts that perform ecocriticism. Rather than merely portraying the ecological status quo, the green humour series actively engages with and responds to the crisis. Just as issues of race, class, caste, and coloniality were sidelined in environmental discourse during its early period, the comic genre was considered an "outsider" in academic terms, not deemed worthy of serious research. Yet it is this very unconventionality, of being non- canonical and defiant of the rules of scholarship and "high art", along with its multimodality and capacity to make readers "bear witness", that make comics an apt genre by which to depict environmental crises <ref type="bibr">(Harpold 2020, 29)</ref>. The "excluded" medium that depicts the lives of the marginalized is thus compatible with its subject matter. In the same way that comics subvert genre expectations, humour and hope subvert affectual expectations in environmental discourses.</p><p>Chakravarty's green humour series is able to translate the frustration and protest of the victims of ecological crises, primarily non-human beings, into humour, thereby humanizing non-human characters and zoomorphizing humans. By placing nonhuman beings at the receiving end of environmental crises as narrators of the three comic books, Chakravarty verbalizes the impact of what Jason Moore (2017) calls capitalogenic intervention from a subaltern, non-human perspective. Moore engages with and expands Andreas <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Malm's (2016)</ref> conceptions of the Capitalocene and fossil capital, highlighting capitalism, overconsumption, resource accumulation, and extractive thinking as underlying factors responsible for the climate crisis <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Moore 2017)</ref>. By addressing the capitalogenic exploitation of the planet in the comic format, the panels, or the individual frames, provide a space for non-human narrators to speak directly to readers, who are themselves silent participants in this exploitation. The comic strips in the series function as micro-narratives, each addressing numerous issues with a variety of characters and multiple voices. This pluriversality <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Leitão 2023</ref>) is instrumental in highlighting multispecies entanglements and fostering solidarity among members of the oppressed underclass. The presence of non-human narrators who speak back directly to the readers and to the "Anthropos" can be read as a mode of resistance against colonial capitalism. These alternative mediums, affects, and modes of "doing environmentalism" when interpreted through an ecocritical, postcolonial, affective framework enable analysis of the humour in Chakravorty's series as ushering in the possibility of slow hope.</p><p>"'Hope' is the thing with feathers": 1 Slow hope, humour(s), and counternarratives</p><p>In the green humour series, animal narrators are presented as dissenters -protesting against colonial capitalist greed and its impact on the environment by holding placards, addressing a gathering, or appealing to readers and the culprits of the environmental crisis. The first chapter of the first book in the series, Green Humour for a Greying Planet <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chakravarty 2021)</ref>, which is based on this theme, is a fitting example. Through the image of protesting animals, some of them endangered or extinct, the perils of the western environmental movement are exposed, because the animals urge that the perspectives of subaltern groups and Indigenous tribes be taken into account in the drive for conservation. Chakravarty portrays a mammoth, an extinct species, meeting some of the animals that exist today. In most such comics, the extinct or endangered animal narrator comments on the contemporary environmental status quo and appeals to humans to curb their disruption of planetary life, thus providing a subaltern dimension. Indeed, Chakravarty foregrounds multispecies solidarity by creating a single group of vulnerable threatened species, who oppose the powerful corporations, capitalists, political leaders, and colonial powers. The unity of the vulnerable underclass is represented as a significant theme. According to Sutirtho <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Roy (2022)</ref>, anthropomorphic animals offer a counter-gaze to human activities and environmental injustice, facilitating a form of posthuman environmental ethics that decentres anthropocentric, conservative frameworks and practices. This marks the inclusion of non-humans into an emancipatory framework that has traditionally been highly human-centred. In the green humour series, animal narrators are anthropomorphized to provide commentary, vent and express frustrations, and engage in discussion, thereby being granted agency and subjecthood to express themselves and explore their victimhood. The human intervention into nature, along with misgovernance, corporate extractions, and capitalistic greed, is questioned and conceived as villainy, prompting readers to empathize with the nonhuman narrators. This drive to change the status quo and accommodate a decolonial, non-human stand points towards decolonial hope.</p><p>In "Indian Pictorial Satire in English", Christel R. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Devadawson (2022)</ref> examines Indian graphic protest and pictorial satire, arguing that "graphic satire certainly goes beyond documentation as it tries to jolt the conscience into action" (n.p.). Animal narrators have been widely used as agents of visual advocacy, protest, and persuasion. The Panchatantra, an ancient book of didactic fables from India, famously employed animal narrators to put across moral messages and commentary on the human society. Using the trope of the animal narrator to inculcate moralistic life lessons to the readers has been a habitual practice in Indian allegories, fables, and children's fiction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Devadawson (2022)</ref> proposes that "the heartbeat of graphic protest throbs through the focalizer: the character through which it argues its case and projects its point of view" (n. p.). The visual protest of animal narrators helps to instil messages of environmental conservation, wildlife protection, and anthropogenic crises. Chakravorty's series can be interpreted as a modern retelling of The Panchatantra, albeit in a planetary context. The animals in his green humour series are not merely rhetorical figures who comment adversely on human society, but they are refashioned as protesters, active agents of planetary politics, who combat and ridicule the human interventions on the planet. Through their agential intervention, the comic form emerges as a channel of resistance against colonial and capitalist structures.</p><p>According to Shreya Sharma and Payel Pal (2024), the green humour comics "subvert the dominant epistemologies of capitalism, and attempt to recenter the margins" (400). One such instance is the comic strip "Elephant Conservation in the First World Way" from Pugmarks and Carbon Footprints <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2023)</ref> in which a conversation unfolds between the British colonial officer and an African elephant held captive 200 years ago when parts of Africa were under British colonial rule (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). The officer proclaims: "O sagacious, majestic creature! This continent of savages is no place for you! Come with me to the world's greatest Nation!" (61). The following panels depict elephants being shipped to Britain. The strip then shifts to the present, where a British official declares that Britain's "conscience has awoken" and it now wishes to "rewild our captive elephants back in your land" by shipping them back to Africa (61). The narrative urges readers to view colonialism as both a human and an environmental event, by reimagining it through the eyes of non-human creatures who were forcibly displaced and exploited. When the British official's request to rewild the elephants is refused, he exclaims: "What? No space, resources or funds to take your own animals back?! [ . . . ] Such a continent of savages!" This exchange lays bare the paradox and hypocrisy of colonial exploitation: Africa is disparaged for lacking resources by the very empire that depleted them.</p><p>The comic exemplifies the hollowness of neocolonial conservation drives and how they mirror the past colonial extractive practices. The white saviour complex of western nations in offering to "save" past colonies from the consequences of colonial exploitation renders this comic strip tragically comic. The lack of accountability and the nonchalance, coupled with colonial extractive logic, is a glaring reminder of the entanglement between environmental injustice and colonialism. The comic's humour, rooted in this paradox of colonial exploitation, exemplifies decolonial humour, through the use of wit to undermine colonial hegemony and its neocolonial legacies, in ways that generate possibilities of decolonial hope. Resistance is borne out of an active and committed effort to change the present scenario. Hope, here, transitions from a passive longing, to the result of a critical engagement with the present unjust status quo.</p><p>"Alterity" is central to Mauch's conception of slow hope, and alternative accounts of collective struggle recur throughout Chakravarty's series. A notable example is the comic strip (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>) about the Amur falcon's migration from East Asia to Southern Africa, featured in the first book, Green Humour for a Greying Planet <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2021, 174)</ref>. The strip celebrates a small but significant victory: previously, migrating Amur falcons were threatened by large-scale hunting in northeast India, but they have since been protected by the collective efforts of local communities (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). These included forming coalitions, naming places after the birds to raise awareness, and ensuring their safety during stopovers. The focus on grass-roots initiatives and collective efforts towards positive change embodies Mauch's slow hope. Importantly, the narratorial voice in this strip belongs to the Amur falcons themselves. The falcons' use of "us" subverts the dominant anthropocentric and colonial narrative voice, which belonged to the privileged white male and relegated "others" to the margins. Chakravarty exemplifies slow hope by appreciating and showcasing the small yet concerted efforts of insignificant creatures that drive positive environmental change.</p><p>Comic effect in green humour is achieved through a range of literary and visual techniques, including parody, irony, sarcasm, role reversal, caricature, trivia, and wordplay. Visually, the series predominantly uses green and grey, a contrast that serves as a stark reminder of environmental depletion. Chakravarty also incorporates new media aesthetics, with some panels mimicking popular social media trends and interfaces, featuring animal narrators. This approach allows the strips to resemble eco-memes in print form. Despite addressing serious themes, the comic format and humorous language make the series accessible to readers of all ages. This accessibility is further enhanced by the use of pop culture references and bitesized information. As the previous examples have illustrated, rather than simply depicting the devastating impact of human intervention, Chakravarty's comics are solution-oriented. Another striking example is the strip "12 Green Resolution Suggestions from Wild Animals", in which animals such as the cattle egret, Bactrian camel, barasingha, and Himalayan black bear offer conservation advice based on their own physical traits and lifestyles. For instance, the Bactrian camel suggests: "Start carrying your own water bottles to avoid plastics" <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2021, 210)</ref>. The uncanny parallel between the camel's water-storing hump and the recommendation of carrying a water bottle creates a comic effect. Additionally, along with attributing agency and "human" characteristics to the animal narrators, the facial features and expressions of the non-human beings are magnified to help readers identify with them and their cause.</p><p>Another important function of humour is self-reflexivity; it enables criticism of the movement from within, rather than treating it as beyond reproach <ref type="bibr">(Seymour 2018, 13-14)</ref>. A major example from the green humour series that embodies what Seymour terms "bad affects" (149) and the self-reflexivity enabled by humour is the comic strip (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>) "Nine Types of Environmentalists" <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2021, 179)</ref>. In this strip, readers encounter a spectrum of environmentalism, from armchair to militant activism to "actual activists" working at the grass roots. The comic strip exposes how the proliferation of self-righteous discourses within the movement can be counterproductive by using irony, exaggeration, and sarcasm. The caption beneath the strip, "Which type are you?", prompts readers to reflect on their own positions and behaviours. Through this illustration, Chakravarty also addresses what Prakash <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kashwan and Aseem Hasnain (2025)</ref> term "mundane environmentalism" as a form of environmentalism expressed through green consumerism and market reforms <ref type="bibr">(14)</ref>. By calling out such superficial tendencies, the comic achieves the self-reflexive function of humour, critiquing the movement and encouraging more substantive critical engagement with the environmental movement from within.</p><p>Images and illustrations have the capacity to bring readers closer to environmental crises. This speaks to another important point highlighted by Dobrin: the quality of "bearing witness" (2020, 13). In many comic strips from the series, readers are directly addressed with the word "you", creating the sensation of a face-to-face conversation. This technique gives the illusion that non-human beings are speaking directly to readers. The meta quality of the comics is further enhanced by the caricaturing of people in key positions, reminding readers that the narrative is not just mere fiction, but rather testimony from non-human narrators based on their lived experiences. This approach fosters a sense of participation, making readers feel like complicit, silent witnesses. As Scott <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">McCloud (1994)</ref> notes in Understanding Comics: The Invisible Art:</p><p>Every act committed to paper by the comics artist is aided and abetted by a silent accomplice. An equal partner in crime known as the reader. I may have drawn an axe being raised in this example, but I'm not the one who let it drop or decided how hard the blow, or who screamed, or why. That, dear reader, was your special crime, each of you committing it your own style. All of you participated in the murder. All of you held the axe and chose your spot. To kill a man between panels is to condemn him to a thousand deaths. <ref type="bibr">(68)</ref><ref type="bibr">(69)</ref> Reading comics is a participatory activity. Unlike the written word, the visual language of comics affords a degree of liberty to the reader's imagination in interpreting the panels. In the green humour series, for instance, the culprits, victims, cause, and consequences of environmental decline are able to be designated by the reader. The author generally does not announce any of these, but gives hints through verbal and visual cues. The rest is up to the reader to interpret. The comics demand deeper reflection and critical engagement on the part of the reader than is typically required by conventional literary forms which rely on authorial explanation. In this series, in many examples, while animals are anthropomorphized, agential beings with their own voices, humans are zoomorphized, creating a sense of role reversal that is almost comical. One notable example is a comic strip about squirrels splooting <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2023, 163)</ref> in which the narrator, a splooting squirrel, appeals to readers, urging them not to panic since "the planet needs some splooting and your species is not helping". This direct confrontation helps make readers feel accountable for humanity's collective failure to address anthropogenic climate change. The narratorial agency of the non-human narrators places the otherwise invisible reader on the spot.</p><p>The consistent use of non-human narrators throughout the green humour series enables readers to move beyond anthropocentric models of environmentalism by foregrounding alterity and marginalized perspectives. However, to fully understand the series' advocacy of decoloniality, Indigenous knowledge systems, and multispecies solidarity in the face of systemic injustices such as colonialism, capitalism, and anthropocentrism, it is necessary to engage with a postcolonial framework. The next section will therefore explore how the comics articulate non-human subjecthood, agency, Indigenous responses to ecological crisis, and subaltern modes of environmentalism using green humour and its close allegiance to both slow and decolonial hope.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Empire, environmentalism, and alternative visions</head><p>Environmentalism is both an ideological framework and a mode of activism, a series of practices concerned with the conservation of the environment and all that it encompasses. Environmentalism cannot be understood as a monolithic term, but means different things to different sections of the population. Postcolonial environmentalism contends that there is no singular way of practising environmentalism; rather, there are multiple environmentalisms. Like many other disciplines, this has been appropriated by the colonial capitalist class, which seeks to make it synonymous with "green capitalism" that creates the illusion of planetary conservation while leaving underlying structures of inequality and injustice intact. Mainstream environmentalism, as a western colonial construct, often engages in frivolous acts of conservation, while failing to address deeper issues such as colonial exploitation, the caste system, Indigenous land rights, imperialism, and gender and sexual injustice.</p><p>Green humour promotes a subaltern mode of environmentalism, one that advocates for modes of resistance aimed at decolonizing, and decentring Eurocentrism. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kashwan and Hasnain (2025)</ref>, in Decolonizing Environmentalism: Alternative Visions and Practices for Environmental Action, argue that mainstream environmentalism is grounded in a Eurocentric world view that privileges the values, ideas, norms, and interests of industrially advanced countries, with an emphasis on individual choices and marketbased solutions. This is precisely why former colonies, still recovering from centuries of exploitation and currently bearing the brunt of resource mismanagement by First World nations, find mainstream environmentalism neither inclusive nor receptive to their needs and voices.</p><p>The interconnection between colonialism and environmental catastrophe is a recurring theme in the green humour series. A comic strip (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>) from the third book in the series, Sea Ice? Now You Don't <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2023)</ref>, features an elderly grandmother and her grandchild observing wind-driven fires wreaking havoc around them (109). The grandmother, with a sombre expression, asks: "Have you noticed how climate change looks and feels the same as colonialism?" Although the question is posed to the grandchild, it is ultimately directed at the reader for contemplation. Chakravarty seeks to expose the intricate connections among all forms of exploitation, be it environmental injustice or colonialism, emphasizing that the most vulnerable will always bear the brunt. This aligns with Naomi <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Klein's (2017)</ref> assertion in her Edward Said lecture that those who are "othered" will be the first victims of the climate catastrophe <ref type="bibr">(35)</ref><ref type="bibr">(36)</ref>. The postcolonial "other", defined solely in relation to the white male colonial "self", is thus more vulnerable to environmental crises.</p><p>In one of his comic strips (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>), titled "Big City Climate Map", <ref type="bibr">Chakravarty (2024, 17)</ref> focuses on environmental injustice: the disproportionate climate crises faced by specific communities, caste groups, countries, and economic classes. The colour palette in this strip is devoid of green; instead, black, grey, and brown dominate, capturing both the doleful mood and the extent of environmental degradation. At the centre of the map, massive concrete structures, chimneys emitting grey smoke, drainage pipes discharging pollutants into water bodies, numerous private vehicles speeding along the roads, and luxury jets streaking across the sky all contribute to a scene of relentless pollution. In contrast, the map's periphery is occupied by the small huts and houses of vulnerable populations, which are both literally and metaphorically marginalized. It is these sidelined groups who become the direct victims of unchecked pollution. While the city centre, home to the rich and privileged, remains under the constant protection of climate policies, the poor are neglected by governments and policymakers. This comic strip illustrates Moore's (2017) concept of the Capitalocene, and his argument that "the rich and the powerful create problems for all of us, then tell us we're all to blame" (6). The comic strip shows that those who contribute the least to environmental degradation are often the most severely affected by its consequences. It highlights how social inequity mediates individuals' experiences of environmental crises (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>).</p><p>Alongside a scathing critique of colonial and capitalist exploitation and its ongoing impacts, Chakravarty also interrogates governmental inaction and irresponsibility in addressing environmental concerns. Part of this negligence stems from a western tendency to treat environmentalism as a stand-alone issue, separate from social justice. The co-option of the environmental movement by corporate interests and political parties is a recurring theme in his comics. Chakravarty is particularly critical of governmental plans and policies that displace and threaten vulnerable populations in the name of conservation. For instance, projects such as the Nicobar Transshipment project and the COP (Conference of the Parties to the UNFCCC [United Nations Climate Change Conference], the countries that signed the original UN climate agreement in 1992) are strongly condemned in the series. The comics on COP can be used as a case study to analyse how Chakravarty engages with issues of race, caste, capitalism, postcoloniality, and environmental injustice. The COP is held annually to discuss and formulate policies to address the anthropogenic climate crisis and its planetary impacts. The government representatives, administrative officials, leaders, and delegates from NGOs (non-governmental organizations) convene each year to address pressing global environmental issues, including but not limited to floods, natural disasters, global warming, fossil fuel exploitation, ocean acidification, pollution, habitat loss, and species extinction ("Conference of the Parties (COP)" 2025).</p><p>Chakravarty's comics, featured across all three books in the green humour series, highlight the shortcomings of recent COP conferences held in Glasgow ( <ref type="formula">2021</ref>), Sharm el-Sheikh (2022), and Dubai (2023). His chief criticism, particularly of COP27 in 2021, targets the hypocrisy of First World nations which, while making grand promises and signing treaties, simultaneously engage in counterproductive practices. A striking example is sponsorship of COP27 by the Coca-Cola Company, a corporation notorious for being the world's largest plastic polluter. Over time, the conference has been accused of greenwashing, promoting an elite, "safe" brand of environmental conservation that addresses issues only superficially. However, in recent years, developing nations have begun demanding funds and compensation from First World countries for their historic and ongoing exploitation of natural resources, exploitation that disproportionately affects poorer nations. For instance, at COP27, Pakistan's climate minister called on wealthy nations to take responsibility for the devastating floods that struck Pakistan that year, demanding compensation for climate-induced losses <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Ebrahim 2022)</ref>. As a result of such advocacy, the "loss and damages" fund was established to assist vulnerable countries in coping with climate change impacts. While this marks a significant achievement for developing nations, progress on other crucial climate action goals and adaptation measures remains insufficient. Through his COP-related comics, Chakravarty emphasizes the disproportionate impact of the climate crisis on poor, postcolonial nations, whose contributions to environmental degradation are minimal yet who suffer the most severe consequences. This global divide leaves these nations vulnerable to the compounded effects of climate change.</p><p>In one of his comic strips on COP (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref>), a black woman preparing to attend COP is shown carrying an enormous burden, both literal and metaphorical, composed of climate change, droughts, floods, livelihood loss, social injustice, heritage loss, and biodiversity loss <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2023, 83)</ref>. Chakravarty conveys that postcolonial attendees and delegates from vulnerable backgrounds are weighed down by the compounded burdens of colonialism, racism, environmental injustice, and natural calamities. The comic also features a white male about to enter COP with a tiny trolley bag labelled "1.5-degree Celsius challenge", who cheerfully proclaims: "I always travel light" <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2023, 83)</ref>. While Third World countries are battling multiple simultaneous crises linked to environmental catastrophe and neocolonial political structures, the only inconvenience faced by First World countries is the need to limit global warming to 1.5 degrees Celsius. As ex-colonies and poorer nations struggle to resist the impacts of climate crisis, the First World finds it difficult to curb its own exploitation of nature. The cruel paradox of this situation is rendered almost comical. The contribution of underdeveloped countries in Africa and Asia to the current environmental crisis is minimal, yet these continents are considered the most vulnerable to the effects of climate change, as noted by the October 2021 Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) report (Climate Change 2021: The Physical Science Basis 2021). According to Anthony <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Carrigan (2015)</ref>, it is not enough to identify "just the agents of natural disasters like cyclones, earthquakes, and floods, among others"; it is essential to address "the social, political, and economic processes that put particular groups at risk and underpin the scale of the disasters" (120). Erik <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Swyngedouw (2014)</ref> has termed this unequal environmental vulnerability the "Oliganthropocene" (n.p.; quoted in <ref type="bibr">Ali 2023, 32)</ref>. This disproportionate impact and experience of the climate crisis form the central theme of many of Chakravarty's COP-related comics, which are also highly critical of the UN's elitist bias and hypocrisy, particularly its failure to listen to the demands of Indigenous groups and vulnerable nations.</p><p>The Indian experience of the environmental crisis is mediated not only by class, gender, place, and race, but also by the inequalities and injustice of caste and other social impediments. Due to their perceived impurity, Dalits have been disenfranchised and pushed to the margins of society, with little or no rights over the natural environment. Chakravarty depicts two intersecting forms of exploitation, caste and environmental injustice; for example, in "Are the Caste System and Conservation Related? In More Ways Than We Think" (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref>), a Bengal tiger delivers a speech on the pervasive impact of caste, particularly within environmental discourse <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty 2024, 5)</ref>. The tiger problematizes the Indian environmental movement's entanglement with caste, highlighting how policies favouring upper-caste interests penalize Indigenous practices such as shifting cultivation and bushmeat consumption, practices far less destructive than the vast biodiversity loss resulting from misgovernance, capitalism, urban expansion, and ecotourism. The Bengal tiger describes conservation frameworks in India as extensions of caste purity and prejudice, but devoid of Indigenous knowledge and expertise. The tiger suggests that "passing the mic" is necessary to reconstruct conservation in India. However, the tiger is interrupted by a leopard, an ostrich, and a frog, who demand that the tiger "shut up and pass the mic". The trope of "passing the mic" refers to allowing victims to speak for themselves, rather than having their struggles appropriated by more privileged voices, an act that further marginalizes the oppressed. In the comic, the Bengal tiger, as India's national animal, symbolizes power and privilege, while the animals interrupting the tiger, an ostrich, a leopard, and a frog, are less privileged. Gail <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Omvedt (1997)</ref> has highlighted the "alienation between two of the most powerful social movements in India: the anti-caste movement and the environmental movement", and the Brahminical allegiances of environmentalist movements and NGOs which have used the environmentalist movement and conservation as a guise to further marginalize the backward caste groups. Echoing similar concerns, Mukul Sharma (2017) conceptualized the idea of "eco-casteism", which he defines as "ecological determinant of caste, provides a rationalization and justification of caste system through nature" (16). Rohan Chakravarty's criticism of the caste bias in the Indian environmental movement is directed towards leading the movement beyond extractive ways of thinking and to encourage receptiveness towards Indigenous voices. The injustices within the environmental movement, such as eco-casteism, point towards a deep-rooted hierarchy that undermines global activist movements. The caste system and colonialism both function on the same principle: systemic discrimination and dehumanization. Consequently, the environmental movement is fundamentally a movement for justice. Decolonial hope aims to eliminate inequalities stemming from colonial injustices and their enduring vestiges. Resistance against caste discrimination and puritanism within the environmental activist milieu seeks to accomplish this same goal. Decolonial hope strives towards the abolition of all systems of inequality, of which the caste system is a central pillar. Ultimately, decolonial hope is impossible without anti-caste hope.</p><p>The animalization of tribal and Indigenous peoples has been a recurring concept in the Indian context. Dalit populations have been compared to animals, or their rights and privileges have been considered less than those of non-humans. During his influential speech at the Mahad Satyagraha, Dr B.R. Ambedkar pointed out that upper-caste Hindus in Mahad prevented untouchables from accessing water from Chavdar Lake because allowing untouchables to drink from it would mean that those labelled as inferior by religious tradition were, in fact, their equals; that they were equally human <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ambedkar [1927</ref><ref type="bibr">(Ambedkar [ ] 1979, 21-24;, 21-24;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Dangle 1992)</ref>. Denying Dalits and Adivasis access to resources is a way of questioning their humanity and stripping them of dignity. Malini Ranganathan (2021) refers to these caste-based practices, which isolate and control Dalit bodies, as "environmental unfreedoms" (258-259). Ranganathan elucidates how environmental politics contributes to the segregation of Dalit neighbourhoods, arguing that caste should be recognized as a central factor in spatial, historical, and political-ecological research.</p><p>The ideas of subalternity, vulnerability, and decoloniality espoused in the green humour series represent a significant step towards making environmental discourse more pluriversal and inclusive. By countering the white, cis-hetero male, colonial gaze through a focus on animal narrators, Chakravarty introduces new ways of envisioning non-human subjectivity and agency, perspectives that are often sidelined in dominant environmental narratives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion: Green humour and slow hope as decolonial tools</head><p>The green humour comics prioritize subaltern modes of conserving the environment through collective, local, sustainable, and grass-roots-level practices, and resist the absolutist and short-term solutions offered by First World countries. The struggle against neocolonialist structures that continue to exploit poorer countries is facilitated by the use of humour, which is a powerful tool of criticism. The use of humour provides an affective alterity in addressing ecological crises, as it is helpful in building a language of hope. The slow hope exhibited in the comics lies in the transformative potential of the resistance posed to western environmentalism by subaltern environmental activism. By envisioning a sustainable present and future that uproot colonial capitalist structures and prioritize non-human perspectives in the environmentalist milieu, the comics espouse a slow decolonial hope which rises above all forms of institutionalized inequality. Humour expresses its activist potential to ignite hope through its incessant attack on colonial hegemony -be it epistemic or environmental. More than a literary tool, it emerges as a mode of epistemic resistance in the texts. Hope is introduced as a sustainable decolonial practice and a political affect in the works under discussion. It is elevated from the stature of a private emotion to the threshold of a collective feeling, especially when introduced as a mode of protest that can disrupt the paralysing narratives of helplessness and agony.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Indigenous knowledge system and climate change (Chakravarty 2020) © Rohan Chakravarty.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,133.17,382.87,226.80,244.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. "Elephant conservation the First World way" (Chakravarty 2023, 61). © Rohan Chakravarty.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,60.89,53.37,371.40,282.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Amur falcons in northeast India (Chakravarty 2021, 174). © Rohan Chakravarty.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,97.80,53.37,297.60,333.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. "Nine types of environmentalists" (Chakravarty 2021, 179). © Rohan Chakravarty.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,60.94,53.37,371.28,360.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Climate change and colonialism (Chakravarty 2024, 109). © Rohan Chakravarty.</figDesc><graphic coords="13,133.17,53.39,226.80,232.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. "Big city climate map" (Chakravarty 2024, 17). © Rohan Chakravarty.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,133.17,53.37,226.80,244.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. I always travel light (Chakravarty 2023, 83). © Rohan Chakravarty.</figDesc><graphic coords="15,133.17,417.61,226.80,209.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure8. "Are the caste system and conservation related? In more ways than we think"(Chakravarty  2024, 5). © Rohan Chakravarty.</figDesc><graphic coords="17,60.94,53.40,371.28,527.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><head>Funding</head><p>The authors reported there is no funding associated with the work featured in this article.</p></div>
<div><head>Notes on contributors</head><p><rs type="person">Arundhathi Baburaj</rs> is a PhD scholar at the <rs type="affiliation">Department of English, University of Hyderabad</rs>, currently focusing on environmental studies. <rs type="person">Girish D. Pawar</rs> is assistant professor at the <rs type="institution">School of Humanities, University of Hyderabad</rs>. His areas of interest are popular culture, new literatures in English, film studies, postcolonial studies and Indian writing in English. He has co-edited Between History and Literature: Essays for Dipesh Chakrabarty (2025).</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Chakravarty's comics, with their decolonial, pluriversal, and polyvocal perspectives, demonstrate that laughter and hope are essential tools in the pursuit of ecological justice.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Note</head><p>1. The title comes from Emily <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Dickinson's (2019)</ref> poem, "Hope Is the Thing with Feathers" (94).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclosure statement</head><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imagining Tropical Cyclones in Fiction: Representation of Cyclone Disaster in Selected Indian Novels in English</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sk</forename><surname>Ali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tariq</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Ecodisaster Imaginaries in India: Essays in Critical Perspective</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Scott</forename><surname>Slovic</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joyjit</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Samit</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maiti</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lexington Books</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">I. Reprinted in Dr. B. R. Ambedkar and His Egalitarian Revolution Struggle for Human Rights</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ambedkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.mea.gov.in/Images/CPV/Volume17_Part_I.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar: Writings and Speeches</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hari Narake</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kasare</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ashok</forename><surname>Kamble</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Godghate</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment, Government of India</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1927">1927. 1979</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Mahad Satyagraha Not for Water but to Establish Human Rights</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Principle of Hope</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ernst</forename><surname>Bloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Neville Plaice, Stephen Plaice, and Paul Knight</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Laughing Matter? Confronting Climate Change through Humor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maxwell</forename><surname>Boykoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Beth</forename><surname>Osnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.polgeo.2018.09.006</idno>
		<idno>2018.09.006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.polgeo" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Political Geography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-09">2018. September</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Branch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199742929.013.021</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199742929.013.021" />
		<title level="m">Are You Serious? A Modest Proposal for Environmental Humor</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press eBooks</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anthropocene Panic: Contemporary Ecocriticism and the Issue of Human Numbers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><surname>Buell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.frameliteraryjournal.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Frame-29_2-Lawrence-Buell.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frame: Journal of Literary Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016-11">2016. November</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a Postcolonial Disaster Studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anthony</forename><surname>Carrigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Global Ecologies and the Environmental Humanities: Postcolonial Approaches</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><surname>Deloughrey</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jill</forename><surname>Didur</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anthony</forename><surname>Carrigan</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cartoons for the Cartoonstock X Red Cross Cartoonathon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rohan</forename><surname>Chakravarty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.greenhumour.com/2020/11/cartoons-for-cartoonstock-x-red-cross.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-11-19">2020. November 19</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Green Humour</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kindle ed. Penguin Books. Chakravarty, Rohan. 2023. Pugmarks and Carbon Footprints. Vintage Books. Chakravarty, Rohan. 2024. Sea Ice? Now You Don&apos;t! Vintage Books. Climate Change 2021: The Physical Science Basis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rohan</forename><surname>Chakravarty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IPCC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Green Humour for a Greying Planet</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Conference of the Parties (COP)</title>
		<ptr target="https://unfccc.int/process/bodies/supreme-bodies/conference-of-the-parties-cop" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025-06-25">2025. June 25</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>United Nations Climate Change</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dr Ambedkar&apos;s Speech at Mahad</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arjun</forename><surname>Dangle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Poisoned Bread: Translations from Modern Marathi Dalit Literature</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Orient Longman</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Indian Pictorial Satire in English</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christel</forename><surname>Devadawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://indianwritinginenglish.uohyd.ac.in/indian-pictorial-satire-in-english/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Indian Writing in English Online</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-04-05">April 5, 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hope Is the Thing with Feathers: The Complete Poems of Emily Dickinson</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Emily</forename><surname>Dickinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Women&apos;s Voice</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Eco-Comix: Essays on the Environment in Comics and Graphic Novels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sidney</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dobrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>McFarland &amp; Company, Inc. Publishers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flood-Hit Pakistan Seeks Loss and Damage &apos;Compensation&apos; at COP27</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zofeen</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Ebrahim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.reuters.com/business/cop/flood-hit-pakistan-seeks-loss-damage-compensation-cop27-2022-11-04/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reuters</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-11-04">2022. November 4</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arturo</forename><surname>Escobar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Pluriversal Politics: The Real and the Possible</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>English ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Apocalypse Reimagined: Visions of Decolonial Hope and Holistic Environmentalism in Nnedi Okorafor&apos;s Lagoon (2014)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Teresa</forename><surname>García-Salcedo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5209/afri.102728</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5209/afri.102728" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Africanías Revista De Literaturas</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102728</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2025-09">2025. September</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Centering Hope as a Sustainable Decolonial Practice: Esperanza En Práctica</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yara</forename><surname>González-Justiniano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>Lexington Books</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Middle Voice of EcoComix: Reading Philippe Squarzoni&apos;s Climate Changed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Terry</forename><surname>Harpold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Ecocomix: Essays on the Environment in Comics and Graphic Novels</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sidney</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dobrin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McFarland &amp; Company, Inc. Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decolonial Hope against the Fourth Industrial Revolution in Edwidge Danticat&apos;s Claire of the Sea Light</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mónica</forename><surname>Jiménez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.12795/ren.2022.i26.12</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.12795/ren.2022.i26.12" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Revista De Estudios Norteamericanos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-01">2022. 2013. January</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decolonial Hope and Planetary Solidarity: Fostering Sustainability through African Life Narratives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Goutam</forename><surname>Karmakar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/17449855.2025.2454571</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/17449855.2025.2454571" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Postcolonial Writing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Decolonizing Environmentalism: Alternative Visions and Practices for Environmental Action</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Prakash</forename><surname>Kashwan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aseem</forename><surname>Hasnain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2025">2025</date>
			<publisher>Bloomsbury Academic</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Let Them Drown: The Violence of Othering in a Warming World</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Naomi</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Will the Flower Slip through the Asphalt</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vijay</forename><surname>Prashad</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>LeftWord Books</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pluriversal Worlding: Design, Narratives, and Metaphors for Societal Transformation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Renata</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leitão</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.25038/am.v0i29.551</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.25038/am" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AM Journal of Art and Media Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">551</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023-04">2023. April</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fossil Capital: The Rise of Steam Power and the Roots of Global Warming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Malm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>Verso Books</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Slow Hope: Rethinking Ecologies of Crisis and Fear</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christof</forename><surname>Mauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5282/rcc/8556</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5282/rcc/8556" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RCC Perspectives: Transformations in Environment and Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2019</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding Comics: The Invisible Art. HarperPerennial. Mignolo, Walter D</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Scott</forename><surname>Mccloud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1215/978147800201</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1215/978147800201" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Foreword to Constructing the Pluriverse: The Geopolitics of Knowledge</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bernd</forename><surname>Reiter</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>On Pluriversality and Multipolarity</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Capitalocene, Part I: On the Nature and Origins of Our Ecological Crisis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jason</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/03066150.2016.1235036</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/03066150.2016.1235036" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Peasant Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="594" to="630" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rob</forename><surname>Nixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Slow Violence and Environmentalism of the Poor</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why Dalits Dislike Environmentalists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gail</forename><surname>Omvedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Hindu</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-06-24">1997. June 24</date>
			<publisher>sec. Opinion</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Caste, Racialization, and the Making of Environmental Unfreedoms in Urban India</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Malini</forename><surname>Ranganathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01419870.2021.1933121</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01419870.2021.1933121" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ethnic and Racial Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can the Non-Human Subaltern Speak? Addressing Injustice through Parakeets, Penguins and Blue Macaws</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sutirtho</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.24193/subbphilo.2022.2.13</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.24193/subbphilo.2022.2.13" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Studia Universitatis Babeș-Bolyai Philologia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="250" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bad Environmentalism: Irony and Irreverence in the Ecological Age</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicole</forename><surname>Seymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mukul</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Caste and Nature: Dalits and Indian Environmental Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ecology at the Margins: Epistemic and Environmental Injustices in Rohan Chakravarty&apos;s Comics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shreya</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Payel</forename><surname>Pal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/21504857.2024.2355942</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/21504857.2024.2355942" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Graphic Novels &amp; Comics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2024-05">2024. May</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Foreword&quot; to Pugmarks and Carbon Footprints by Rohan Chakravarthy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Akanksha</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<pubPlace>Vintage</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anthropocenic Promises: The End of Nature, Climate Change and the Process of Post-Politicization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Erik</forename><surname>Swyngedouw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lecture at the Center for International Studies and Research (CERI)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Paris</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-06-02">2014. June 2</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
