<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Orality and the subaltern: Anticolonial resistance in Rosario Cruz-Lucero&apos;s Feast and Famine: Stories of Negros</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Aimee</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Farah</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Virador-Cagayan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Humanities</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of the Philippines Mindanao</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Davao</settlement>
									<country key="PH">Philippines</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of the Philippines Mindanao</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Tugbok Dist</addrLine>
									<settlement>Brgy Mintal, Davao del Sur 8000</settlement>
									<country key="PH">Philippines</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Orality and the subaltern: Anticolonial resistance in Rosario Cruz-Lucero&apos;s Feast and Famine: Stories of Negros</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5969F94F59403CF1AE660CDDA0BE5C1F</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1080/17449855.2025.2586099</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2026-02-25T19:53+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Pluriversality</term>
					<term>peasant consciousness</term>
					<term>oral traditions</term>
					<term>historical fictions</term>
					<term>colonial modernity</term>
					<term>anticolonial resistance</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Rosario Cruz-Lucero's Feast and Famine: Stories of Negros decolonizes historical narratives by centring the lived experiences and oral traditions of marginalized communities in Negros Island, Philippines. The collection highlights how peasant workers and local storytellers resist the displacement, marginalization, and erasure of Indigenous systems of knowledge under colonial and neoliberal regimes. Through forms of orality such as composos, epics, gossip, and oraciones, Cruz-Lucero reconstructs historical imaginaries that challenge dominant narratives rooted in racial capitalism and elite historiography. These oral forms, often dismissed as nonserious or irrational, emerge in her stories as vital repositories of cultural memory, survival, and anticolonial resistance. Framed through the lens of pluriversality, the stories assert ways of knowing and being that resist the totalizing logic of capitalist modernity. Cruz-Lucero's work reveals how oral traditions serve not merely as cultural residue but as active instruments in confronting epistemic violence and reimagining decolonial futures from the margins.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>they fail to subscribe to a "universal" or mainly western assumption of rationality. This invalidation, I contend, serves to silence working-class and Indigenous voices and erase their histories, as their knowledge systems and cosmologies are deemed incompatible with the dominant national narrative. The forced assimilation into a homogenized national culture in the Philippines, along with the privileging of capitalist interests in a neo-liberal economy, further entrenches their marginalization.</p><p>The first section of this article situates Indigenous resistance in Negros within a broader historical context, demonstrating how colonialism and capitalist expansion have systematically marginalized Indigenous communities. Building on this foundation, the next section explores how Feast and Famine uses oral narrative forms -traditionally passed down through generations in Indigenous communities -as a means to resist and challenge the dominant historical narratives that have displaced Indigenous systems of thought. These oral traditions offer alternative ways of understanding history, emphasizing communal memory, storytelling, and lived experiences that counter the linear, progress-driven accounts typically associated with colonial modernity. The last section of this article argues that folk consciousness, deeply rooted in Indigenous spirituality and oral traditions, plays a crucial role in decolonizing historical narratives and asserting pluriversality as praxis. Pluriversality, a term popularized by the Latin American decolonial group Modernity/Coloniality -particularly in the works of Walter <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Mignolo (2011)</ref> and Arturo <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Escobar (2018)</ref> -refers to the coexistence of multiple epistemologies, cosmologies, and lifeworlds beyond the singular logic of western modernity. As Mignolo emphasizes in The Darker Side of Western Modernity, pluriversality is to a universal project in the plural, one that resists epistemic hegemony and affirms the legitimacy of alternative ways of knowing and being. Escobar, in Designs for the Pluriverse, similarly underscores how pluriversality emerges from the lived experiences and worldviews of Indigenous and other marginalized communities. Framing pluriversality as praxis not only challenges the epistemological dominance of colonial modernity but also reaffirms the importance of Indigenous knowledge systems in the ongoing resistance against cultural erasure and marginalization.</p><p>Previous studies of Cruz-Lucero's Feast and Famine have focused on the text's use of interlanguage, as evidenced in Cruz-Lucero's refusal to translate Hiligaynon 1 concepts <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Villareal 2013</ref>); on how, as "vernacular literature", this text uses spirit-lore as part of its imaginative repertoire <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Villareal 2010)</ref>; and on how the narrative establishes intertextual links between history, theology, and postcolonial literary criticism in one of its stories <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Wright 2007)</ref>. However, such an approach does not touch on how the stories use forms of orality to present a pluriversality of consciousness as a way to decolonize history and narrative. Focusing on the narrative's intertextuality, this analysis precisely examines how the text challenges monolithic conceptions of history and postcolonial identity. In other words, I analyse how Cruz-Lucero's work suggests that Indigenous resistance, spirituality, and folk consciousness continue to offer alternative narratives that disrupt and challenge the dominance of capitalist and colonialist structures. In the next section, I will discuss the different layers of critique showing how Cruz-Lucero offers a systematic analysis of the colonial knowledge system. In doing so, she posits the pluriversal as a valuable alternative to universalist discourses anchored mainly to western assumptions of rationality and progress.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Enduring struggle and resistance: Peasant uprisings and the fight for land in Negros</head><p>Following Spain's distribution of Negros Island to 17 encomenderos 2 in 1571, the native population consistently resisted Spanish colonial rule to maintain their autonomy and way of life. From the late 16th to the early 19th century, Indigenous communities led sporadic uprisings against Spanish friars and missionaries, who aimed to eradicate what they perceived as pagan practices among the natives. The Spanish encomienda system, which imposed forced labour and tributes on the local population, was met with specific resistance from Indigenous communities. They continued to live according to their traditional sociopolitical structures centred around kinship and communal land ownership <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Alcina and Lietz 1960;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Lachica 1996)</ref>.</p><p>Leading this opposition were the babaylanes, spiritual leaders regarded by the people as mediators between the spiritual and physical worlds <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Cullamar 1986)</ref>. Following the arrival of Spanish colonizers, the babaylanes and their followers faced persecution as part of efforts to eliminate pagan practices. Some of the most prominent of these babaylanes were Estrella Bangotbanwa, who was believed to have the power to summon rain after months of drought, Dupinagay and Tapara, Monica Gapon, and Augustina Hiticon, who all led armed struggles against foreign invaders seeking to impose their religion and ways of life on them <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Regalado and Franco 1973)</ref>. By refusing to submit to the monolithic imposition of colonial religion and culture, these leaders and their followers preserved their ways of life and knowledge systems, demonstrating that Indigenous epistemologies and cosmologies are as valuable as those of the colonizers.</p><p>Despite persecution, remnants of the babaylan tradition persisted even to the present day, continuing to influence peasant consciousness and resistance. In March 2024, for instance, babaylans from the Estrella Bangotbanwa Babaylan in Iloilo province in the Philippines performed a "Pana-et" by invoking the names of spirits and datus or tribal chieftains in early Philippine societies, chanting for rain to alleviate the heatwave and dry spell exacerbated by the El Niño climate phenomenon <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Yap 2024)</ref>. They performed this in the area where Fr Isidro Badrena, an Augustinian priest, died in April 1874 after trying to stop the babaylans from performing the ritual. The mystical powers of Estrella Bangotbanwa remain prominent in the local lore in the Panay and Negros regions. In Cruz-Lucero's Feast and Famine, the figure of the babaylan can be detected in the namesake characters of Estrella in "The Death of Fray Salvador Montano" and Estrella the binukot in "Doreen's Story", who is implied to be the same Estrella as in "The Death of Fray Salvador Montano", as well as Estrellita in "The Oracle of the One-Eyed Coconut" and Tiya Estrella in "The Composo of Hacienda Buyung" who can be deduced as descendants of the character Estrella in the first two stories. These characters, as portrayed in Cruz-Lucero's short stories, indefatigably resist and/or undermine colonial modernity's imposition of beliefs and political systems, specifically those of women's role in society and of the capitalist system. In doing so, they serve as the people's spiritual healers and leaders, even if they have been relegated to the margins of the community.</p><p>In Cruz-Lucero's work, I contend, this recovery of Indigenous beliefs in babaylans or shamans, tamawos or mythical creatures who have white skin, and anting-anting or amulets, constitutes a deliberate attempt to create pluriversal knowledge, a concept pervading the entire short story collection. By reviving and recentring the spiritual and cosmological practices of figures like the babaylanes, Cruz-Lucero challenges the dominant epistemes conveyed by colonial modernity.</p><p>Following the opening of the Suez Canal and the development of steamships in the 19th century, there emerged a growing demand for sugar in the global market <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Darwin 2020)</ref>. As local economies became more integrated into global systems, focusing production on cash crops like sugar in order to meet international demand led to the expansion of plantations. This was particularly true in colonies like the Philippines, where cheap labour and land were exploited to maximize production and profits. As Alfred <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">McCoy (1992)</ref> points out, large areas of land in Negros were devoted to sugar-cane cultivation. An economic boom led to the rise of a wealthy class of landowners who had control of most of the province's land, capital, and labour. These sugar planters came mainly from the Chinese mestizos of Iloilo, Molo, and Jaro districts of nearby Iloilo province. In contrast, their sugar plantation or hacienda workers came from the neighbouring islands of Panay, Bohol, and Cebu.</p><p>The hacienda workers consisted mainly of indios naturales, or the Spanish socio-legal category for the largest segment of native people who were not of ethnically mixed descent. According to Filomeno <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Aguilar (2019)</ref>, these workers can be classified into two groups: the agsas (also known as acsas, agsadores, aparceros) or the sharecroppers, who were the permanent resident workforce in the haciendas, and the jornaleros or day labourers, who provided labour of a temporary kind, especially during harvest and crude sugar claying seasons (122). This labour division was widely enforced from the 1850s until the early 1900s, even with restrictions to mobility caused by the internal passport system that required indios to seek permission to travel from their cabeza de barangay (village head), gobernadorcillo (town magistrate), alcalde mayor (provincial governor), and cura parroco (local parish priest) (124).</p><p>In spite of such restrictions, the importation of labour from nearby provinces caused the population of Negros to increase by four and a half times in only half a century. Indeed, there were also indocumentados or undocumented labour consisting of indios who connived with planters to sacar or extract illegal labour from neighbouring islands. This process of extracting labour from neighbouring islands gave currency to the term sacada, which at present refers to transient migratory workers in Negros Island. From 9000 in 1867, the number of undocumented labourers increased to 35,500 in the 1890s, which made up a sizable portion of Negros population (Echauz 1894).</p><p>The end of the 19th century saw the rise of Indigenous resistance movements led by babaylanes. The best known of them was led by Papa Isio or Dionisio Magbuelas. Initially a babaylan, Papa Isio emerged as a revolutionary leader during the Negros Revolution. Declaring himself the "Pope of Negros", he led his followers, the pulahanes, in a series of attacks against Spanish forces and sugar-cane plantation owners. His rebellion was motivated by a desire to end Spanish exploitation, particularly the oppressive labour conditions on the sugar plantations, and to restore Indigenous ways of life eroded by colonial rule <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Lachica 1996)</ref>.</p><p>Following the fall of Spanish colonialism and at the beginning of American colonial rule, Papa Isio carried on with his resistance against the new colonial power, refusing to recognize American sovereignty. However, his struggle only lasted until 1907, when he was captured by American forces and later imprisoned. In contrast to Papa Isio, the character of Estrella in Cruz-Lucero's Feast and Famine remains in the tapestry of Negros society, albeit sometimes on the sidelines. She continues to perform her role as the people's spiritual healer, albularya, sacamuela, and binukot.</p><p>With most land already encroached upon by the expanding sugar industry in the 20th century, the workers could no longer flee to the hinterlands as they used to in earlier times. This possibility was also restricted by the virtual disappearance of the frontier and the significant increase of the population of Negros province from a little more than 100,000 before the opening of the Iloilo port in the 1850s to over 1.1 million in 1939. Therefore, many agsas or share tenants eventually became dumaan or wage-dependent labourers who resided on the hacienda's premises. Since these dumaans were already dependent on the hacienda system, they no longer looked for other means of living elsewhere. Indeed, few other options were available to them on the island. The succeeding generations of these wage workers also became accustomed to a life of dependence, subservience, and poverty, which led to their "deproletarianization" <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aguilar 2019)</ref>. They identified with the hacienda where they were born. In this process, they learned to address the planters as toto (brother) or inday (sister), as if they were part of this "fictive familial community" (139).</p><p>During World War II, Negros served as a site of significant guerrilla resistance against the Japanese occupation. The Indigenous populations of the island, already skilled in the use of the island's rugged terrain for defence, joined the guerrilla movements, contributing to the broader national struggle for liberation from Japanese forces. These resistance efforts were marked by a strong sense of local identity and autonomy, with guerrilla units often operating independently and relying on local knowledge and resources. However, after more than three centuries of colonial rule, the hacienda system became deeply entrenched on Negros island, where large estates, controlled by a few powerful families, dominated the agricultural landscape. This created a stark divide between the landowners and the hacienda workers, who were often forced into debt and servitude. Despite the long-standing oppression, hacienda workers continuously struggled to assert their rights, facing fierce resistance from hacienda owners, who used intimidation, violence, and legal manoeuvres to maintain control.</p><p>This fierce opposition from hacienda owners sought not only to maintain economic control but also to preserve a social order that placed them at the top of a rigid hierarchy. In this respect, the sacada system served to perpetuate the exploitation of workers. Indeed, it devised modern forms of labour control, binding workers into cycles of debt and servitude that echoed the earlier struggles for land and autonomy. Despite various land reform efforts, this system of contractual labour effectively deprived workers of security and rights, ensuring that the power dynamics established during colonial times remained unchallenged. Wealth and land ownership remained in the hands of the elite. For the workers, reclaiming their lands was not only a fight for economic survival but also a struggle for justice and self-determination. Despite facing violent reprisals and legal challenges, the determination of peasant workers to fight for their rights persisted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Depicting anticolonial defiance through forms of orality</head><p>My approach emphasizes how orality in Feast and Famine functions not only as resistance but also as an archive of pluriversal historical consciousness. The use of forms of orality in decolonizing historical narratives, I contend, allows for the reclamation and validation of Indigenous and folk knowledge systems that have been marginalized or dismissed in colonial texts. Among those forms, one can list community-based oral traditions grounded in displacement, survival, and solidarity, such as sugilanon or folk tales and composos or ballads, ritual healing practices such as oraciones that combine addresses to Catholic saints and pre-Christian deities, as well as anting-anting or amulets. Finally, the way in which women storytellers serve as keepers of folk knowledge plays a major role. These women destabilize haciendero "official" history by retrieving subaltern lifeworlds -rituals, rumours, supernatural accounts, and famine survival knowledge. In this way, they highlight the perspectives and experiences of those Indigenous peoples and peasant workers that colonial modernity considers as peripheral to its rigid vision of the world.</p><p>Orality, as argued by Walter J. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Ong (1988)</ref>, facilitates communal memory, immediate engagement, and a participatory mode of meaning-making. He writes that "persons in a primary oral culture can entertain some sense of proprietary rights to a poem, but such a sense is rare and ordinarily enfeebled by the common share of lore, formulas, and themes on which everyone draws" (131), emphasizing the social and embodied dimensions of oral culture. Postcolonial and decolonial scholars such as Ngũgĩ wa <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Thiong'o (1986)</ref> and Mignolo, on the other hand, point out how orality serves as a counterhegemonic tool against colonial domination. Wa Thiong'o insists on the decolonization of the mind through the recovery of Indigenous languages and oral traditions, arguing that "orature has its roots in the lives of the peasantry. It is primarily their compositions, their songs, their art, which forms the basis of the national and resistance culture during the colonial and neo-colonial times" <ref type="bibr">(1986,</ref><ref type="bibr">95)</ref>. Mignolo similarly asserts that "racialization is applied not only to people, but to language" (2007, 17), pushing for epistemic disobedience as a way of rejecting Eurocentric knowledge systems.</p><p>Unlike Ong, who highlights orality's cognitive structures, or Wa Thiong'o and Mignolo, who foreground its political and epistemic ruptures, I focus on how oral narratives in Cruz-Lucero's text reconfigure history itself -foregrounding affect, memory, and Indigenous relationality as valid modes of world-making. Here, orality is not merely a vehicle of transmission or resistance but a generative, meaning-making practice that recasts marginalized lifeworlds as sites of historical narration and theorization.</p><p>Throughout Feast and Famine, Cruz-Lucero blends oral traditions with literary techniques, creating hybrid forms that bridge orality and literacy. As pointed out by Jack <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Goody (1993)</ref>, orality and literacy coexist and shape each other within specific societies. The short story collection's narrative structures, which incorporate composos or ballads, gossips, police reports, and oraciones or prayer chants, demonstrate Cruz-Lucero's use of syncretic forms to reclaim a historical path deviating from or subverting dominant interpretations of history. For instance, in "Doreen's Story", the narrative interweaves police reports, a form associated with state authority and legal rationality, with prophetic pronouncements from a One-Eyed Coconut that provide oracles through oraciones, syncretic spiritual practice blending Catholic prayer and folk mysticism. Such forms reveal how Cruz-Lucero merges colonial bureaucratic language with oral and spiritual traditions to expose tensions between official state discourse and popular knowledge. These narrative modes are maintained through the "colonial matrices of power" <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Quijano and Ennis 2000)</ref> that foreground the Eurocentric perspective of history, but Cruz-Lucero subverts them by foregrounding hybrid, localized epistemologies. The use of oral traditions as narrative forms illustrates how the indios, and later the peasant working class, consistently engaged in varying degrees of subversion and defiance against the imposed consciousness of colonial modernity. In Feast and Famine, orality enables Cruz-Lucero to construct a pluriversal knowledge system where claims to truth are expressed in a more nuanced fashion. Indeed, orality presupposes community, which in turn immediately suggests a diversity of voices and perspectives.</p><p>In the short story "The Death of Fray Salvador Montano", for instance, Cruz-Lucero shows how during the Spanish colonial period, local epics were shared by the people, even though they already started losing significance due to the imposition of a colonial culture and religion. The indios were perplexed by the depiction of heroes as "scoundrels" and women as "shape-shifters" in the Humadapnon epic on Buyung Labaw Dunggun and Nagmalitung Yawa <ref type="bibr">(Cruz-Lucero 2003, 31)</ref>. Humadapnon is one of the three epics of the Hinilawod from the Panay Bukidnon people of the Visayas in the Philippines. Passed down through generations by binukot or secluded, highly trained female oral chanters, the Hinilawod epics recount the adventures of three demi-god brothers, Labaw Donggon, Humadapnon, and Dumalapdap. In the Humadapnon cycle of the epic, Humadapnon embarks on a long and arduous journey to seek a bride, encountering enchantresses, sorcerers, and shape-shifting women along the way. Among the most striking figures is Nagmalitung Yawa, a beautiful and cunning warrior-woman who uses her magical abilities -including shapeshifting -to rescue Humadapnon and defeat his captors.</p><p>This deviation from typical colonial or western portrayals of heroism and femininity, as noted by Cruz-Lucero, perplexed the converted indios, because in their eyes, these figures did not conform to ideals of Christian virtue or linear moral development. The epics apparently no longer reminded them of anything, as they "could no longer hear their 'mother's voices' trapped in their bone marrow" (8). For them, "Bard and Bore had become the same" <ref type="bibr">(Cruz-Lucero 2003, 8)</ref>. The appearance of foreign religion and diseases on the island further marginalized the local culture and practices. Unable to cure these foreign diseases, Estrella, the village baylan, agreed to be baptized so she could collaborate with the priest in healing her people. In return for urging the natives to abandon their "bastos songs", Estrella asked the priest to allow the natives to "sing their epics again" (11). However, these epics had become so unfamiliar to the people that even Estrella could no longer retrieve their endings. While they had evolved into composos, these epics resulted in songs whose fluid endings kept changing over time. As these narratives were already measured by Christian moral standards, Estrella could no longer continue singing them. Indeed, they could be bearers of the natives' history and culture as a people in the sense of capturing their changing beliefs and lifeways after colonial invasion and the advent of Christianity.</p><p>However, through the composos, the peasant workers asserted their traditions and subverted colonial thought. These narratives, communally produced and shared, intermingled colonial and Indigenous world views. In the same story, the indios alternate between the heroes of their local epics, specifically Labaw Dunggon, and the figure of the friar Fray Duertas:</p><p>Fray Montano was not surprised when, soon enough, composos began to reach his pueblo about the wondrous ways in which Fray Duertas, from his new parish of Pueblo Minuluan, was making people fly through limestone crags, over bodies of water, and under the green canopy of jungles-all without the aid of the monsala scarf, betel nut chew, or the busaw's golden strand of hair that were the vehicles by which the indios grandparents had once transported themselves from one place to another in an instant. <ref type="bibr">(Cruz-Lucero 2003, 12-13)</ref> The indios singing of the composos challenge colonial power dynamics, as can be inferred from the description of Fray Montano as the "fat and lazy fraile of Pueblo Buyonan, who spent his days sleeping in his convent, sleeping through the Mass, sleeping in the confessional" ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>). These composos held much power in the people's life and imaginings because they were being sung around the island, from the coastal village of Hunob-Hunob in the north to the mountain fastness of Kanlaon in the south. When a traveling manugcomposo took it to a tabuan, where the people converged to barter their goods, another one would pick it up and take it to the next tabuan, where Duertas' feat took on even more miraculous proportions. ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) However, as Cruz-Lucero knows, these power relations were inherently unequal, as the Spanish exploited the indios to serve their colonial ends. They were forced to repress or forget their ways of knowing and living in order to simply survive, and this led to a displaced and alienated consciousness. While remnants of their communal activities and practices persisted in their subconscious through their language and stories, they could no longer make sense of them as they used to, because of the negative influence of a foreign language, religion, and culture.</p><p>In "Doreen's Story", on the other hand, gossips play a crucial role in creating and developing stories belonging to the community during the American colonial period in early-20th-century Philippines. They perform a similar role in the temporal context of the story where the characters Doreen, Jonathan, 3 and one who can be presumed to symbolize Rosario Cruz-Lucero herself are sharing stories about a hacienda heiress named Anabella. This story recounts how the townspeople of Negros constructed narratives. When something happened in their town, they took time "to recover before they [started] ripping the narrative seams apart so they could peer into whys and wherefores" <ref type="bibr">(Cruz-Lucero 2003, 44)</ref>. Thus, the people created their legends and histories, which would define and shape their consciousness as a community.</p><p>This story illustrates how the American colonial rule transformed not only the physical landscapes but also the existing social hierarchy in Negros. The introduction of public education led to the rise of the middle class from the ranks of the working class, as exemplified by Francisco. He is first described as one of the "penniless children of plantation workers" (35), but later becomes the town dentist. Both public education and public health systems thus lead to the reshaping of the socio-economic landscape, cultural norms, and aspirations of the native people in Negros. However, as the new colonial state relied on the local elites to pacify their new colonial subjects, the American colonial period mainly solidified the power and dominance of the sugar planter class by backing their appeals for the reorganization of the sharecropping system. This prevented plantation workers from having an equal share in the hacienda profits. Instead, they became wage workers reliant on the plantation owners for their survival. This is illustrated by Don Isidro, Anabella's father, who uses his ikog sang pagi, or sting ray's tail to punish errant workers on his hacienda. However, his workers still consider him as "a fair and generous amo" or boss:</p><p>When a worker was whipped fifty times, we said he was being given "two cavans", because one cavan 4 you know, was equal to 25 gantas. But still, Don Isidro was a fair and generous amo. Everyday he watched to see who would do karga-tapas the fastest, and if the worker kept it up for a whole month, he was given two cavans at the end of the month. Real ones." And the old man pointed to himself and laughed gleefully. Then he shrugged. "Every man has his tool of the trade. I had my espading. He had his ikog sang pagi." <ref type="bibr">(Cruz-Lucero 2003, 32)</ref> The embedded story in "Doreen's Story" underscores Cruz-Lucero's illustration of how stories are shaped by the realities of their storytellers, specifically Doreen who tells the story of Anabella to her friends Jonathan and the narrator, the townspeople who have their stories to tell about Anabella and her family, and the storyteller, who is implied to be Cruz-Lucero herself. The characters freely change the narrative's direction, adding, omitting, or changing the details of the story after various forms of interruption. The latter may comprise a question from a friend, a research finding about a specific topic, or the death of the storyteller, Doreen Fernandez, a famous literary critic Cruz-Lucero had befriended. Thus, Cruz-Lucero subverts conventional narrative norms and structures by reversing assumptions about the ending to Anabella's story. To this end, she indicates that Anabella persisted in writing fiction and poetry, in spite of all the stories narrated about her. In doing so, Anabella rejected the demands of her parents and society that she remain an heiress.</p><p>Or, when Anabella dies on September 14 next year, she will be discovered to have written 72 novels, 122 short stories, 7 novelettes, 5 corridos, 8 narrative poems of l100 to 1,000 stanzas each, 231 short lyrics, 7 long plays, 24 short plays and dialogos in verse, 7 volumes of essays, and 2 autobiographies. My generation needs its own legends too. <ref type="bibr">(Cruz-Lucero 2003, 48-49)</ref> Anabella, like the mermaid Bukay Ati or Estrella the arbularya in the story (or perhaps even more so), embodies the narrative of the binukot. The presence of these cloistered females in Indigenous societies dominates local epics <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abrera 2009)</ref>. The binukot are known as chanters of tales and bearers of ancient and traditional wisdom. Indeed, their isolation from the community has made them more spiritually aware, enabling them to serve as mediators between the physical and spiritual worlds.</p><p>Therefore, the use of gossip as a fictional form can be decoded as Cruz-Lucero's means of highlighting the interplay between oral and written narratives. Estrella the arbularya, the known binukot in the text, shares stories with Anabella through chanting, showing the interaction between orality and literacy. She also insists on the link between Anabella and Doreen through the structural device of gossips, thus moving from literacy to orality. Likewise, she foregrounds the relationship between Doreen and Rosario Cruz-Lucero, when choosing to switch from gossips to short story as a narrative form.</p><p>Similarly, the portrayal of Anabella throughout "Doreen's Story" displays Cruz-Lucero's desire to reimagine history. In order to achieve this, she focuses on the perspective of female characters and writers who shaped the local literature and history of Negros. An instance of this method is the intertwining of the lives of Adela Ledesma, who is Cruz-Lucero's basis for the character of Anabella, the heiress whose ill-fated love story became a town legend, and Magdalena Jalandoni, who became one of the most prolific writers in the Hiligaynon language <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Nite 2019)</ref>. In this way, Cruz-Lucero not only reclaims the female narrative but also challenges colonial and patriarchal impositions on how history and cultural memory are transmitted.</p><p>Just as the binukot in precolonial society facilitated the preservation of epics and oral traditions, Cruz-Lucero restores their importance in her literary world. This recuperation of the female as a custodian of oral traditions is also deeply rooted in the broader historical resistance to colonialism. While Indigenous communities opposed the displacement of their lands and cultures, Cruz-Lucero's use of orality functions as a form of intellectual and cultural resistance. Her characters, particularly Anabella, Estrella, Doreen Fernandez, and herself embody the continuity of Indigenous knowledge systems, as they reject the erasure brought about by colonial modernity.</p><p>By contrast, in "The Oracle of the One-Eyed Coconut", Cruz-Lucero foregrounds the perspective of those who lived during the time of Martial Law in 1970s Philippines through the structure of a police report. A certain Captain Baby Baltazar documents the viewpoints of each character implicated in the mayor's murder. This narrative structure illuminates the intersecting experiences of the individuals caught in the sociopolitical turmoil of the time, while also foregrounding the resilience of Indigenous cosmologies and practices through repeated allusions to Estrellita's One-Eyed Coconut.</p><p>Moreover, the period of martial law was marked by the presence of the New People's Army (NPA), the Civilian Defence System (CDS), and the Civilian Home Defence Forces (CHDF). Gun-for-hires also contributed to an atmosphere of random and systemic violence, making survival uncertain for many people in Negros. This especially affected the poor and even the "less wealthy", as violence served to protect the interests of the landed elite. Extreme poverty caused thousands of children and infants to die of malnutrition, exacerbating the people's sufferings. Religion began to influence political debates, as religious leaders intervened in public affairs, delivering politically charged sermons that impacted people's attitudes. The military's role in society also grew, as the number of paramilitary groups who served the landed elites increased. The disappearance of youths and individuals suspected of being communist sympathizers highlights the fear and uncertainty that pervaded everyday life in Negros, Philippines, in the 1970s to 1980s.</p><p>Folk spiritualities, however, remained strong, as exemplified by Estrellita's reliance on her One-Eyed Coconut to reveal oracles and to signal impending doom and catastrophe. The One-Eyed Coconut helped her find the corpses of the nine boys accused of being communist insurgents in the sugar-cane field. It also showed her visions of what happened to them as the desaparecidos or the disappeared. Oracles, by contrast, are dismissed as mere beliefs in favour of the objectivity and rationality of police investigations. The use of police reports as narrative structure contrasts with the One-Eyed Coconut's oracles. This shows how these two forms of orality intersect, both shaping people's lives during a period of social and political upheaval. As Estrellita uses oracions, leaves and roots to heal people, she is thought to be a witch who eats her children. Even though she tells people she is not such a monster, she is still constantly referred to as a "witch", whose beliefs and practices deviate from rationality: "But you're a witch yourself, aren't you?" Peejay mumbled, his eyes already shut. When he had a stomach ache, all she had to do was mumble an oracion and blow into his big toe and the ache would go away. When he was hot with fever and he vomited all the medicine that his mommy would spoon into his mouth, she would wait until everyone was gone and she would take from her magic bag of leaves and roots just the right thing to douse the fire in his body. <ref type="bibr">(Cruz-Lucero 2003, 53)</ref> Nonetheless, those people from her community who cannot afford the medical services in the town centre, and whose lives are considered expendable, still regard her as a healer. As Estrellita's oraciones and the oracles from the One-Eyed Coconut are dismissed as mere witchcraft and sorcery, those who choose to think otherwise are treated as pawns who can be eliminated for their inability to contribute to an economy of endless capital accumulation.</p><p>In the novella "The Composo of Hacienda Buyong", the locals' perspectives on their history are revealed through their performance of composos, which blend myth and history, undercutting any notion of a single truth and objectivity. The text illustrates how the townspeople spend their time gossiping and sharing composos. It points to the ways in which these stories have evolved over the years, accruing new endings, versions, or meanings. Each composo is shown to be deeply rooted in the distinct experiences and cultural backgrounds of its storyteller, showing how stories transform and adapt as they are passed down from one storyteller to the next:</p><p>From the bag of jewels clasped in Toto Kiko's hand sprang many legends that slowly grew branches all around it, many of them sinking to the ground, weighed down by the many rings of truths they carried, each one taking root in the fertile soil of the people's imaginings. When Tiya Estrella began to sing the opening lines of the composo of Toto Kiko, people would gather 'round her store, ready to listen to a story they had already heard hundreds of times but ready, too, to be surprised at a new twist to it or a continuation to a story that they thought had already been brought to closure. "O mga señores kag señoras, Pamati-i ninyo, akon iga-asoy ining higugma ni 'To Kiko" [O, ladies and gentlemen! Listen, as I sing to you the love story of brother Kiko]. <ref type="bibr">(Cruz-Lucero 2003, 85)</ref> This aggregative and dialogic form of composos demonstrates how oral traditions evolve into more inclusive and multidimensional forms, challenging the monolithic narratives imposed by colonial modernity. The peasant workers gather to sing and share composos and to talk about the changes happening in their community. The latter involve the construction of a shopping mall over the top of a mass grave for cows. Indeed, the workers were told shopping malls would help attract foreign tourists and would prompt them to invest in Negros. The changes also include the tale of Toto Kiko's bag of jewels, and the tragic fate of Estrella, the people's babaylan, who was massacred by the Spanish soldiers accompanying Fray Duertas, as well as disappearances and rescues of individuals who were accused of being communist insurgents during the period of Martial Law in the Philippines.</p><p>Unlike written historical accounts that aspire to fixity and authorial control, composos accumulate new versions, endings, and perspectives, as they are communally devised, reshaped, and transmitted through oral performance by the people singing them. As the veracity of the details may shift with each retelling, their authority lies not in factual accuracy but in their capacity to affirm communal memory and respond to collective emotional and social realities. By emphasizing this fluidity, Cruz-Lucero resists the colonial-modern imposition of a singular, linear history, and instead foregrounds a pluriversal mode of storytelling that centres the sensibilities of communities historically relegated to the margins. For these communities, beliefs embedded in composos are not quaint cultural artefacts but lived, tangible realities.</p><p>As each storyteller provides a different interpretation or ending of the story, Cruz-Lucero highlights the sensibilities of disenfranchised people. For them, their beliefs are real and tangible. However, colonial modernity, in its attempt to control the subjectivities of the "uncivilized", has distorted the meaning of these beliefs, turning them into mere curiosities <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Chattopadhyay 2024)</ref>. Cruz-Lucero's work subverts this tendency by positioning oral traditions as legitimate sites of historical knowledge and cultural resistance. Earlier critical receptions of Feast and Famine acknowledge this intervention, specifically Lawrence <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Ypil's (2003)</ref> "Unframing the House of History", which foregrounds the metafictional dimensions of "Doreen's Story" and reads it as symptomatic of local historiography, narrative mediation, and the instability of historical truth. Similarly, the review of Feast and Famine by Ma. Teresa <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Pineda (2004)</ref> highlights the collection's use of oral traditions and genre hybridity. Both works note how the collection destabilizes hegemonic national narratives and affirms the epistemic integrity of Indigenous and working-class world views.</p><p>In other words, the collection's composos kept accumulating and evolving, as the people constantly modified them. They freely added to them, showing the aggregative aspect of oral traditions. Although nobody really knows who caused what and why, the peasant workers gather to discuss and entertain themselves with the composos and all their mutable narratives. There is not one single truth to tell, but a plurality of versions revealing the sensibilities of peoples who were displaced to the fringes of society. In the same way as the composos allow the characters to reclaim their voices, the stories they tell collectively challenge the dominant narratives that have sought to silence and dismiss their experiences. The gathering of peasant workers seeking to entertain themselves with the composos inherited from oral tradition underscores the community's agency in creating their own historical narratives, even if they remain fragmented and everchanging. This, I contend, underscores the pluriversal idea that there are multiple, coexisting ways of knowing and understanding the world. By emphasizing the communal nature of orality, Cruz-Lucero insists that knowledge is decentralized and shared by the people, rather than imposed from above.</p><p>This alternative system is rooted in shared values, Indigenous cosmologies, and a deep connection to the land, all of which stand in opposition to the exploitative structures of the hacienda system and neo-liberal capitalism. Thus, in Cruz-Lucero's work, orality serves not only as a form of storytelling but also as a critical tool for decolonizing knowledge. This recuperation of native resistance ties into the historical context of colonialism, in which oral traditions played a crucial role in maintaining Indigenous sociopolitical structures and cultural memory. While Indigenous and peasant uprisings constituted forms of direct resistance to colonial powers, the preservation and transmission of oral traditions also served as a form of intellectual opposition. They asserted the value of pluriversality and the role of oral knowledge in disrupting and challenging colonial narratives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion: Storytelling as resistance and renewal: Pluriversal futures in</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Feast and Famine</head><p>In Rosario Cruz-Lucero's Feast and Famine, the Indigenous anticolonial lifeworld is revitalized through an emphasis on oral traditions connecting the seemingly diverse and disparate stories set on the island of Negros. Through the lens of pluriversality, it highlights the coexistence of multiple systems of knowledge and ways of being and counters the homogenizing forces of colonial modernity and global capitalism. Cruz-Lucero depicts how Indigenous and peasant communities continue to organize themselves in ways that reject the individualism and commodification central to capitalist economies.</p><p>By revisiting and reimagining anticolonial resistance, Cruz-Lucero indicates how the legacies of colonialism persist in contemporary times, albeit in more covert and systemic forms. Her recovery of anticolonial struggle serves as a reminder that the fight against oppression is ongoing. Indeed, the regaining of the anticolonial spirit of opposition goes beyond the fact of merely reclaiming past struggles: it also asserts the validity of these alternative epistemologies and lifeways in the present. In this way, in a world marked by ecological collapse and deepening inequality, Feast and Famine offers not only a counterhistory of Negros, Philippines but also a foregrounding of community-based epistemologies rooted in land, story, and kinship, aligning itself with movements in global decolonial thought that regard storytelling not only as resistance, but also as renewal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Notes</head><p>1. One of the major Philippine languages spoken predominantly in Panay Island, Negros Occidental, and Soccsksargen with more than 9.1 million speakers. 2. Encomenderos were Spanish colonial agents granted control over specific territories and the Indigenous populations within them under the encomienda system, which functioned as a tool of both economic extraction and sociopolitical domination during the early Spanish colonial period in the Philippines. 3. These protagonists can be decoded as Doreen Fernandez and Jonathan Chua, respectively, who are respected literary critics and known to be friends of Cruz-Lucero. 4. A unit of mass or dry measure for rice equivalent to 60 kg or 75 litres.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclosure statement</head><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Notes on contributor</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Farah</head><label></label><figDesc>Aimee S. Virador-Cagayan, PhD, is an assistant professor of English at the University of the Philippines Mindanao where she teaches comparative literature and Philippine arts and culture. Her research interests include 21st-century Philippine historical fictions and decolonial studies. She has published her work in UNITAS Journal, and the University of Mindanao Interdisciplinary Research Journal; an article in Philippine Studies: Ethnographic and Historical Viewpoints is forthcoming.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="14" xml:id="foot_0"><p>F. A. S. VIRADOR-CAGAYAN</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seclusion and Veiling of Women: A Historical and Cultural Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Abrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bernadette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://journals.upd.edu.ph/index.php/pssr/article/download/1274/1630" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philippine Social Sciences Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Peripheries: Histories of Anti-Marginality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Filomeno</forename><surname>Aguilar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>Ateneo de Naga University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Francisco</forename><surname>Alcina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ignacio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Historia de Las Islas E Indios de Bisayas</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Anthropology, University of Chicago</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Demystifying the &apos;Pluriverse&apos; as the Hegemony Unravels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sahana</forename><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://medium.com/age-of-emergence/demystifying-the-pluriverse-as-the-hegemony-unravels" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-02-19">2024. February 19, 2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Age of Emergence. f85b93dd605e</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Reader in Philippine Film: HIstory and Criticism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Chua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rosario</forename><surname>Cruz-Lucero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rolando</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Tolentino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>University of the Philippines Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Herstory [Essays]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rosario</forename><surname>Cruz-Lucero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Babylan Woimen&apos;s Pub. Collective</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Feast and Famine: Stories of Negros</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rosario</forename><surname>Cruz-Lucero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>University of the Philippines Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">La India, or Island of the Disappeared</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rosario</forename><surname>Cruz-Lucero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>University of the Philippines Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Evelyn</forename><surname>Cullamar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Babaylanism in Negros, 1896-1907</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cellar Book Shop</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Unlocking the World: Port Cities and Globalization in the Age of Steam</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Darwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1830" to="1930" />
			<pubPlace>Penguin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Apuntes de La Isla de Negros [Microform]. Internet Archive</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Echaúz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://archive.org/details/apuntesdelaisla00collgoog/page/n17/mode/2up" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Tipo-litografía de ChofrDoe y Comp</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1894">1894</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arturo</forename><surname>Escobar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Designs for the Pluriverse: Radical Interdependence, Autonomy, and the Making of Worlds</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Interface between the Written and the Oral</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Goody</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Panay&apos;s Babaylan: The Male Takeover</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><forename type="middle">Milagros</forename><surname>Lachica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Geremia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Women&apos;s Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sugar Barons: Formation of a Native Planter Class in the Colonial Philippines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alfred</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mccoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/03066159208438490</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/03066159208438490" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Peasant Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Walter</forename><surname>Mignolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Darker Side of Western Modernity: Global Futures, Decolonial Options</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Delinking: The Rhetoric of Modernity, the Logic of Coloniality and the Grammar of De-Coloniality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Walter</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mignolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09502380601162647</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/09502380601162647" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cultural Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="514" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Works of Magdalena G. Jalandoni: A Bibliography and Library List</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">St</forename><surname>Nite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Evangelista</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.13185/2244-1638.4430</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.13185/2244-1638.4430" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philippine Studies: Historical and Ethnographic Viewpoints</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="482" to="490" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Orality and Literacy: The Technologizing of the Word</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Walter</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Philippine Studies: Historical and Ethnographic Viewpoints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ma</forename><surname>Pineda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Teresa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.13185/2244-1638.2410</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.13185/2244-1638.2410" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="137" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rosario Cruz-Lucero, Feast and Famine</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coloniality of Power, Eurocentrism, and Latin America</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anibal</forename><surname>Quijano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Ennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/23906" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nepantla: Views from South</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="533" to="580" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Felix</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Regalado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Quintin</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Franco</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">History of Panay. Iloilo</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
			<publisher>Central Philippine University</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Philippines</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Demons, Saviours, and Narrativity in a Vernacular Literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Corazon</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Villareal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.31436/asiatic.v4i2.522</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.31436/asiatic" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asiatic: IIUM Journal of English Language and Literature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="0522">2010. 4i2.522</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Listening to the Overheard: Phillipine Literatures into English</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Corazon</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Villareal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of English Studies and Comparative Literature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Decolonising the Mind: The Politics of Language in African Literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wa</forename><surname>Thiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">'</forename><surname>Ngũgĩ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>Heinemann</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London; Portsmouth, NH</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pursuing the Pleasure of the Story: Reading Rosario Cruz-Lucero&apos;s &apos;The Death of Fray Salvador Montano, Conquistador of Negros&apos;</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Teresa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/13488678.2007.10801213</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13488678.2007.10801213" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asian Englishes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shamans Gather in Iloilo for Good Friday Ritual</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tara</forename><surname>Yap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://mb.com.ph/2024/3/30/shamans-gather-in-iloilo-for-good-friday-ritual" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Manila Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024-03-30">2024. March 30</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unframing the House of History: The Metafiction of Rosario Cruz-Lucero&apos;s &apos;Doreen&apos;s Story&apos;</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><surname>Ypil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Loyola Schools Review: School of Social Sciences</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Victor</forename><surname>Venida</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Office of Research and Publications</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Ateneo de Manila University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
